<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Noahs doue, or Tydings of peace to the godly A comfortable sermon preached at a funerall. By Samuel Smith minister of Gods word at Prittlewel in Essex.</title>
            <author>Smith, Samuel, 1588-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110828</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846296</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846296</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11256</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12529)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11256)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1671:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Noahs doue, or Tydings of peace to the godly A comfortable sermon preached at a funerall. By Samuel Smith minister of Gods word at Prittlewel in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Samuel, 1588-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, and are to be sold by Thomas Archer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11256:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11256:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NOAHS DOVE, OR, Tydings of Peace to the godly.</p>
            <p>A comfortable Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at a Funerall.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Smith</hi> Miniſter of Gods word at <hi>Prittlewel</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 34.19.</hi>
               </bibl> Many are the troubles of the righteous, But the Lord deliuereth him out of them all.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Archer.</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11256:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11256:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, as it hath euer bin the practice of wicked men to make their proſperity an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods fauour, reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after this manner: Is it likely that I ſhould inioy ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſsings from God if my conuerſation were not pleaſing in his ſight, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.2.</note> Not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:11256:3"/> that theſe common gifts are giuen alike both to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man and to the ſinner: And that <hi>Eſau</hi> though he was a man hated of God, yet enioyed the fatneſſe of the earth as well as <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>So the children of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the outward proſperity of the wicked, and their owne miſerable condition here in this life, haue hereby beene much troubled; and haue beene mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to call Gods Iudgements into queſtion, how it could ſtand with his Iuſtice that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men ſhould ſo abound in wealth that <hi>Rebelliouſly tranſgreſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 12 1. Pſal. 37.</note> This prooued a
<pb facs="tcp:11256:3"/> ſore temptation vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> inſomuch that he confeſſed that his <hi>ſteps had wel-nigh ſlipt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.2.</note> And the ſame thing perplexed the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> that hee was bold euen to reaſon the caſe with God, ſaying;<note place="margin">Ier. 12.1</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore doth the way of the wicked proſper, &amp; why are they in wealth that rebelliouſly tranſgreſſe?</hi> Many of Gods ſeruants are not a little affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted herewith, not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the reaſon, how the Lord will not ſuffer his children in this life to goe vnchaſtiſed for their ſinnes, but thereby brings them to a greater meaſure of humiliation: As for the wicked,
<pb facs="tcp:11256:4"/> the Prophet aſsigneth a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their proſperity, namely this,<note place="margin">Ier. 12, 3.</note> 
               <hi>That thou maieſt pull them out like beaſts for the ſlaughter, and prepare them for the day of Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> This truth is moſt cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet downe in the ſeauen and thirty <hi>Pſalme,</hi> a portion whereof I haue handled in the Sermon following, my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire herein is to comfort Gods people, that notwithſtanding their preſent condition may ſeeme to bee miſerable, yet the Lord doth euer vpholde his in time of greateſt danger, and of this they ſhall be ſure, that their <hi>later end ſhal be peace.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:11256:4"/> I wiſh thee comfort by it, and by all other holy helpes. And ſo remayne</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in euery Chriſtian office,</hi> Samuel Smith.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Prittlewel,</hi> 
                  <date>this <hi>8. of April, 1619.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:11256:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11256:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM. 37.37.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Marke the vpright man, and behold the iuſt: the latter end of that man ſhall be peace.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author of this Scripture, as all other the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, is the Spirit of God: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Apoſtle; <hi>All Scripture is giuen by inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>and is profitable for Doctrine, for reproofe, for correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for Inſtruction in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that the man of God may be perfect in all good workes.</hi> The Inſtrument that the holy Ghoſt vſeth for the penning of it. It
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:11256:6"/> ſeemes to be the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> A princely Prophet of the Lord, and that <hi>Sweet ſinger of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The argument of the Pſalme is an Exhortation vnto all Gods people, that are ready many times to be grieued at the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of the wicked, and at the afflictions of the godly. For men are but men, &amp; haue their infirmities, a thing not to bee wondred at.<note place="margin">Iob. 4.18.19.</note> For as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde hee found no ſtedfaſtneſſe in his ſeruants, and layd folly vpon his Angels; How much more in them that dwell in houſes of clay.</hi> And amongſt many other infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that the godly are ſubiect vnto here in this life, this is not the leaſt, that they grudge and repine at the proſperity of the wicked, whom they finde to be free from troubles, and as for outward proſperity, to <hi>floriſh
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11256:6"/> like a greene Bay tree,</hi> which makes the godly to thinke that they haue cleanſed <hi>their heart in vaine.</hi> Now againſt theſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults and temptations, Gods ſpirit doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence vs &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthen vs in this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> giuing vs to vnderſtand, that howſoeuer the wicked haue here abundance of proſperity for a time, it is but for a time. For hee ſheweth that all <hi>euill doers ſhall bee cut off,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhort time <hi>ſhall no where be found.</hi> How proſperouſly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the wicked may liue for a time, hee affirmes that their fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity is but vaine &amp; tranſitory: for being in their ſinnes and not in Gods fauour, in the ende are ſure to bee deſtroyed with the reſt of Gods enemies. And on the contrary part, how miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoeuer the eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the godly ſeemes to bee
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11256:7"/> in this world, yet being in Gods fauour, <hi>their end ſhall be peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Pſalme diuides it ſelfe into three parts.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Parts of the Pſalm.</note>Firſt, an Exhortation to the weake, that they bee not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, nor diſquiet themſelues at the proſperity of the wicked; and the affliction of the godly; and this is layd downe from the firſt verſe to the 7. verſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, hee ſheweth that how proſperouſly ſoeuer the wicked doe liue for a time, yet their preſent felicity is vaine &amp; tranſitory, and ſuddenly ſhall come to an end. From the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth verſe to the eleuenth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he ſheweth that how miſerable ſoeuer the godly ſeem to liue in this world, yet ſhall ſtill be preſerued, and <hi>their end
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11256:7"/> ſhall be peace.</hi> To the end of the Pſalme.</p>
               <p>The verſe wee haue in hand containes in it matter of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that we diligently <hi>marke</hi> and <hi>behold</hi> the <hi>vpright man,</hi> the man that is godly religious, makes conſcience of holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; that in all things labours to <hi>keepe a cleere conſcience before God and all men,</hi> that howſoeuer this man be exerciſed with ſore afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vndergoes much hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at the hands of others, bee neglected or little regarded, yet <hi>the later end of that man ſhall bee peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The verſe hath in it two parts.</head>
               <p>Firſt, the matter of obſeruation, who is it the Holy Ghoſt would haue vs to take ſuch notice of, not the Noble, the Rich, or the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:11256:8"/> Mighty, but the <hi>Vpright</hi> and <hi>Iuſt man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the end wherefore we ſhould ſo diligently obſerue him, namely, that wee might be incouraged in wel-doing, and not diſcouraged vnder our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent afflictions, ſince hee is ſure to haue <hi>peace at laſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt of theſe which is the matter of obſeruation, I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the note of attention, <hi>marke</hi> and <hi>behold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the perſon to bee obſerued, the <hi>vpright</hi> and <hi>iuſt man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, the Holy Ghoſt ſeeketh to awaken our eyes, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally are very drowſie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold any thing that is good, and to prepare our hearts, which are firſt to be ſought vp, before wee can goe about Gods buſineſſes.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:11256:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marke</hi> and <hi>beholde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. The note of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</note> theſe words of attention make known vnto vs that there is ſome waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie matter within this Text, which Almighty God would haue vs well to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of For ſo indeed in the ſacred Scripture, theſe two words <hi>marke</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> are euer vſed vpon extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie occaſions.</p>
               <p>Now this ſerues to put vs in minde of our owne dulneſſe and backwardneſſe to good duties,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> that wee thus ſtand in neede of ſuch prouocations to put vs in minde of the ſame; precept vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on precept, and line vpon line, and all too little to prouoke vs to good duties. If our hearts be duly poſſeſt with diuine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, a man can neuer caſt his eyes amiſſe, whether wee looke to the heauens aboue, or to the earth belowe, or vpon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11256:9"/> what creature ſoeuer, ſtill wee haue Gods Phyloſophy Lecture read vnto vs in the Creature, to teach man his dutie towards his Creator.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. The perſon.</note>But amongſt all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures whatſoeuer, the Lord ſends vs to beholde man to this ende, that wee ſhould <hi>marke</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider</hi> what is Gods manner of dealing towardes the ſonnes of men, both in his puniſhing of the wicked, and rewarding the godly; <hi>Marke the vpright man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> The Doctrine is, that euery Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in a ſpecial maner to obſerue what is Gods dealing with men,<note place="margin">Gods dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with men muſt be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> both with the godly and with the wicked, as well thoſe that are recorded in Gods Booke, as thoſe that we haue knowne in our owne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience: and that to this ende, that wee might bee incouraged
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11256:9"/> in the wayes of godlineſſe by the examples of the godly, the Lord highly honouring them with a bleſſed memory vpon earth, and crowne of glory in heauen. As alſo diſcouraged in committing of ſinne, when we ſhall conſider Gods feareful Iudgements inflicted vpon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: how the name of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doth rot, and how the Lord doth pay and repay Iudgement, wrath, and indignation, vpon ſinners. We muſt not be ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of Gods dealings in the world, but duely to record his workes and dealings with men, not onely to ſee and behold the ſeuerity of God towards others, but for ſpectacles and examples to vs, that we ſhould take heede of ſuch ſins which procure ſuch iudgements. And to this ende wee ſee in the Scriptures the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11256:10"/> Lord hath hung vp in chaines, as it were, diuers wicked men, not for others to gaſe vpon them, but to be warned by them. For murtherers <hi>Caine</hi> is hung vp:<note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> For all prophane perſons <hi>Eſau</hi> is made an example: For traytors <hi>Iudas:</hi> For all Apoſtates <hi>Lots wife:</hi> And ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> telleth vs that <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> and the Cities about them, which the Lord deſtroyed for following ſtrange fleſh, were and are ſet foorth for a warning and example to all filthie and beaſtly minded men. The like may be ſayd of <hi>Iſmael, Gehezi, Abſalom, Saul, Achan,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>And as we are to obſerue the wicked, ſo eſpecially to <hi>marke</hi> and <hi>beholde</hi> the godly, their godly life, their ſober conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and their care and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11256:10"/> to walke with God, in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his commandements, their admirable faith, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full patience, meekeneſſe, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, &amp;c. Theſe things muſt be obſeru'd by vs, that ſo we may by their examples be incoraged in the waies of well doing, &amp; in them may ſee that our labour ſhal not be in vaine in the Lord: and to this end the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſets out vnto vs a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of very memorable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of deedes of Gods worthy ſeruants; you haue heard <hi>of the patience of Iob</hi> ſaith <hi>Iames:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 5. Heb. 11</note> and in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> there are diuerſe remembred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that were famouzed in their times for their faith, &amp; ſtill remaine in a bleſſed memory in Gods Church, and ſo ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for euer. And ſo likewiſe to take notice of the graces of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11256:11"/> God in his ſeruants that remain with vs, <hi>beholde</hi> their liues, and <hi>behold</hi> their ends, as an incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement vnto vs in walking in their <hi>pathes.</hi> Howſoeuer the godly are afflicted heere for a time, <hi>the latter end of that man ſhall be peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I come to the reaſons of the Doctrine.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, concerning the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the wicked, eſpecially of the godly: This may be one principall reaſon why wee muſt <hi>marke</hi> them well, for the manner of their life, and for the manner of their deathes; becauſe God is not mutable and changeable, but euer the ſame without any ſhadow of change. As the Lord heretofore and daily doth bring ſhame and confuſion vpon the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11256:11"/> heades of wicked men and ſo makes them examples vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo will the Lord deale with vs if wee treade in their pathes: the ſame iudgements of God that ouer-tooke other ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſhall in the ende ouertake thee if thou walk in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er waies. Seeſt thou a man that hath been a graceleſſe wretch, a horrible ſwearer, an vncleane perſon, a prophane perſon or the like: hath the Lord followed ſuch with his Iudgements, as their life hath beene without grace, ſo their deathes haue been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out comfort, <hi>behold</hi> in them thy owne condition, remember that God is iuſt, the ſame iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments waite vpon the ſame ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
               <p>So eſpecially as my Text ſaith concerning the godly, <hi>Marke well the righteous, and behold the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:11256:12"/> iuſt. Beholde</hi> their life, and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde</hi> their death, if their liues haue beene religious, though accompanied with many out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward afflictions, their deathes haue neuer wanted comfort: <hi>The end of that man ſhall be peace.</hi> And let the ſame incourage thee in well doing, becauſe God is not mutable,<note place="margin">Acts 10.</note> hee changeth not, <hi>In euery nation hee that feareth God and worketh righteouſnes is accepted of him:</hi> follow ſuch in their life, &amp; thou ſhalt not miſſe of their comfort in thy death, <hi>grace</hi> in life and <hi>peace</hi> in death.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, by theſe are the men that God delights in, theſe feare him, theſe honour his Name, theſe haue learned firſt to ſeeke the kingdome of God and the righteouſneſſe thereof, theſe do not diſgrace the Goſpell and holy profeſſion of Chriſt, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11256:12"/> therefore <hi>marke well</hi> theſe men.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it may be ſayd of the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> godly as it was ſayd of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that they are <hi>men after Gods own heart,</hi> theſe are they that haue learned to deny vngodlineſſe, and worldly luſt, and liue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly and iuſtly in this preſent world: In a worde, theſe are the beſt ſtateſmen, theſe vpholde a kingdome, bring a bleſſing to the towne &amp; countrey wherein they liue. Theſe God doth ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as the apple of his eye, theſe are as neere to him as the ſignet of his right hand, whom hee daily follows with his bleſſings, and will neuer leaue them till they haue the ful fruition of him in glory, and therefore <hi>marke theſe men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I come to the vſes of the Doctrine.</head>
               <p>Firſt, it ſerues for matter of <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:11256:13"/> reproofe vnto thoſe that in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſtories of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon others in the Booke of God, and obſeruing the like daily in their owne experience, make not this vſe of them to make them beware: many won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at them that they had no better grace, but alas they doe not heereby take occaſion to feare Gods iudgements, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them to themſelues, &amp; to ſay in their hearts, this example is ſet out to warne me and to teach mee, that if I commit the ſame ſinne God is iuſt ſtill, I ſhall bee ſure to partake of the ſame pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and ſo to breake off their ſinnes by repentance. But alas, though wee ſee and heare daily of neuer ſo many fearefull examples of Gods iudgements againſt ſinne and ſinners, where is the man that ſaith, alas, <hi>What
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11256:13"/> haue I done?</hi> for farre are many from <hi>marking</hi> Gods dealing with others.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this miniſters mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> of inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto all, that we <hi>marke well the vpright:</hi> It is the counſell the Holy Ghoſt giues vnto vs heere, followe them as they haue followed God, bee carefull to imitate their vertues, ſo ſhalt thou bee ſure to pertake of their praiſe:<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Our labour ſhall not be in vaine in the Lord, He is a plentifull rewarder of them that ſeeke him.</hi> And euer remember that God is vnchangeable, true, hee that ſtood by them and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them out through all their miſeries and afflictions, will bee as ſtrong in thee if thou be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to walke with him as they haue done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:11256:14"/>
               <head>Marke the vpright man, and behold the iuſt.</head>
               <p>The next thing wee are here to take notice of, is the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a godly man, or that man that eſpecially is to be <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</hi> hee is an <hi>vpright man,</hi> and a <hi>iuſt man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe titles wee ſee are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent &amp; often vſed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the Lord doth honor his ſeruants with them, whence we are taught this inſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> That Gods ſeruants in this life may attaine vnto that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace and ſanctication,<note place="margin">Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants may be called vpright men and iuſt here. Iob. 1.1. Luk. 1. Act. 10. Heb. 11.38</note> as that they may truely be called <hi>vpright</hi> and <hi>iuſt men.</hi> Thus doth the Lord commend <hi>Iob</hi> to bee an <hi>vpright</hi> and <hi>iuſt man:</hi> It was the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendations of <hi>Zacherie, Cornelius,</hi> &amp; diuerſe others men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Scripture.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:11256:14"/>
               <p>Which Doctrine indeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues to bee vrged and preſſed to ſtop the mouthes of thoſe that are euer diſgracing Gods people with their taunts, Oh you are holy, you are an <hi>vpright man,</hi> you are a <hi>iuſt</hi> man: but herein they deſpiſe not man but God, who hath holineſſe in his ſeruants,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>without which no man ſhall ſee God.</hi> But if I ſhould ſtand vpon this point I ſhould bereaue you of ſome other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction more fitter for this preſent occaſion, which I would willingly impart vnto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſo I come to the ſecond part of the verſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The later end of that man ſhall be peace.</head>
               <p>Theſe words containe in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reaſon why we ſhold ſo dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11256:15"/> obſerue the <hi>vpright man, The later end of that man ſhall be peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of this Reaſon I obſerue two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the ſpeciall time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing, God will take care of the godly at all times, yea thogh the Lord doe ſuffer them to lie vnder affliction for a time, hee is not then vnmindfull of them: But their later end ſhall haue a double rewarde.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I note the bleſſing it ſelfe, which ſhal be conferred vpon them,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.13.</note> it is <hi>peace,</hi> the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt bleſſing, and that which go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth beyond all other bleſſings, for it paſſeth all vnderſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Latter end of that man ſhall be peace.</head>
               <p>The Prophet hauing before
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:11256:15"/> exhorted vs to <hi>marke</hi> and <hi>behold</hi> the life of the <hi>vpright man</hi> and <hi>iuſt man,</hi> comes now to ſhewe wherein hee is happy aboue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>hee ſhall haue peace. Peace</hi> is promiſed vnto him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, as a iuſt recompence of his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe and faſtneſſe: this he ſhall bee ſure of, Sathan, the world, nor his owne corruption ſhall neuer be able to take it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, it is an inſeparable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of grace and vertue, haue thou grace, thou ſhalt be ſure of <hi>peace.</hi> But marke heere, it is at their <hi>latter end:</hi> they are not ſure of it at all times, no, no, Gods ſeruants are heere in a warfare, they are to fight againſt the Diuell, and a world of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, and as our Sauiour teacheth,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.33.</note> 
                  <hi>In the world you muſt haue tribulation,</hi> but <hi>The latter end ſhall be peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:11256:16"/>
               <head>The Doctrine is.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label>
                  <note place="margin">The godly in this life haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</note>That good men, yea the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Gods Saints and ſeruants in this life ſhall haue troubles, &amp; ſore affl ctions, which they bear ſo much the more grieuous when on euery ſide the wicked ſhall abound in pleaſure. This was it that ſo troubled <hi>Dauid</hi> at this time, and before hee won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at the proſperity of the wicked, and on the contrary part was much caſt down to ſee what a loade of afflictions lay vpon the godly: but now he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couers himſelfe with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of this, that howſoeuer Gods people ſuffer much for a time, it is but for a time, yea a ſhort, they ſhall bee ſure to haue <hi>peace at laſt.</hi> And now hee hath learned this leſſon, and can teach it others: That looke how
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11256:16"/> many will truely feare the Lord, that carefully will endeauour to walke in Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the end of their dayes, they ſhall haue croſſes and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,<note place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note> ſo true is that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>That all that will liue god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Chriſt Ieſus muſt ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution. Innumerable troubles</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) haue compaſſed mee from my youth (may Iſrael now ſay) they haue oftentimes afflicted mee from my youth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 40.12</note> 
                  <hi>but they could not preuaile againſt mee.</hi> I might inſtance this Doctrine by infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite examples, <hi>Abraham</hi> in exile, <hi>Iob</hi> on the dunghil, <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the priſon as a malefactor in an high degree, <hi>Ieremy</hi> in the ſtocks, <hi>Daniel</hi> in the denne, the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> euen the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable bondage vnder the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians:</hi> So that I conclude, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11256:17"/> look how many of vs as inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be righteous, we muſt looke for afflictions and troubles, yea and prepare our hearts thereunto, &amp; not to bee diſmayed at them when they fall vpon vs, had though ſome ſtrange thing had happened vnto vs, according to that of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, think it not ſtrange concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the fiery tryall which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you to prooue you, as though ſome ſtrange things were come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. But reioyce in as much as ye are pertakers of Chriſts ſufferings, that when his glory ſhall appeare, ye may be glad and reiocye.</hi> I ſhall not neede I hope in ſo euident a truth to ſearch vp more Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to proue it: The Reaſons that follow will cleare the ſame vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe the godly haue in them many ſinnes, for ſinne is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11256:17"/> the generall and vniuerſall cauſe of all troubles, for ſo teſtifieth the Prophet ſaying;<note place="margin">Lam. 39.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Man ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for his ſinne, let vs ſearch &amp; try our waies and turne vnto the Lord.</hi> So then in as much as all haue ſinned, all are lyable to chaſtiſements &amp; afflictions, the iuſt puniſhment of ſinne, and if wee breake his Satutes and keep not his Commandements, no maruaile though the Lord doe viſit our iniquities with his rod, and our ſinnes with ſcourges.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe the godly <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> haue many graces, for as God doth beſtowe vpon his ſeruants more gifts &amp; graces then vpon all the worlde beſides, ſo will the Lord haue the ſame to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in his ſeruants to the praiſe of his grace. They muſt be beat like ſpice in a motter that they may ſauour the better, and euer
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11256:18"/> according to our ſtrength, the Lord doth euer proportion our tryals,<note place="margin">On Hoſ. 6.1.</note> but I haue handled this elſewhere.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The conſideration of this is for excellent vſe vnto the godly, to comfort them in the midſt of all their troubles and afflictions here, that they doe not thereby iudge of Gods fauour or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure: for as <hi>Salomon</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>All things happen alike to all.</hi> It is the condition of the godly as wel as the wicked, yea, it is more inſident to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and profeſſion of the Goſpell then to others. Such muſt not thinke the worſe of themſelues, but the better, onely they are to labour to make their calling and election ſure, that hauing aſſurance of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in Ieſus Chriſt, they may thereby haue their afflictions
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11256:18"/> ſanctified vnto them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this may ſerue to <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> comfort the faint-hearted, that are toſſed with the waues of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny troubles heere; if ſearching their hearts they can finde their vprightneſſe, and trying their owne waies they prooue to bee righteous, there is not that cauſe of ſorrow or diſcontent to that man to thinke his ſtate ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſperate or irrecouerable. If troubles were alwaies an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of Gods diſpleaſure, who then were ſure of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour; The Lord doth as ſure prouide his children correction as food, and hee that is without chaſtiſement is a baſtard &amp; not a ſonne. Let no man then ſay in proſperity, I ſhall neuer bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued: God hath his quiuer full of arrowes to ſhoot abroad. Neither let any in aduerſity ſay,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:11256:19"/> I ſhall neuer bee reſtored. For the Lord taketh no pleaſure in afflicting his ſeruants, whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the Lord chaſtiſeth his, he ſees there is great neceſſity of the rod, yet in the middeſt of iudgement the Lord remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth mercy, &amp; howſoeuer ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row may indure for a night, ioy commeth in the morning, <hi>Their latter end ſhall be peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The latter end of that man ſhall be peace.</head>
               <p>The Second thing wee are to take notice of,<note place="margin">Peace the greateſt bleſsing of God.</note> is the bleſſing it ſelfe, which ſhall bee conferred vpon them, it is <hi>peace,</hi> the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt bleſſing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But ſhal not the <hi>later end of all men</hi> be alike? doth not <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.1</note> 
                  <hi>There is one end to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and the wicked, to the cleane
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11256:19"/> and vncleane, to him that ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth and to him that ſacrificeth not, the end is all alike:</hi> why then ſhall the <hi>later end of the vpright be marked</hi> more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other mens?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwere that their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end is all alike for the matter of their death, that is,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> all doe die: But it is not all one for the manner of their death, for all ſhall not die in <hi>peace,</hi> but as my Text ſaith; <hi>Marke the vpright man and beholde the iuſt, for the later end of that man ſhal be peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then the inſtruction we are to take notice of hence, is,</p>
               <p>That the godly onely at their <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> later end haue <hi>peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Onely the godly haue peace at laſt.</note> ſo that wee haue heere to conſider what is the condition of all men in death: all die, but all haue not <hi>peace</hi> in their deathes, <hi>The later end of the iuſt ſhall bee peace.</hi> But as for the wicked, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 48.22.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:11256:20"/> 
                  <hi>There is no peace to the wicked ſaith my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I deſire briefly to ſpeake of both of theſe.</p>
               <p>And firſt concerning the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Holy Ghoſt doth heere aſſure them of <hi>peace,</hi> &amp; that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vpon their going hence they are happy,<note place="margin">Reu. 14.13</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord, from thenceforth they reſt from their labours.</hi> This appeares in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to whom it was promiſed that hee ſhould goe vnto his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in <hi>peace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 15.15</note> And of <hi>Iſaac</hi> his ſonne it is ſayd,<note place="margin">Gen. 35.29</note> That he gaue vp the ghoſt and died <hi>peaceably,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing old &amp; full of dayes: The like may bee ſayd of <hi>Iacob,</hi> of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> of <hi>Ioſuah, Moſes, Dauid,</hi> and it is true of all Gods ſeruants, that their latter end is <hi>peace.</hi> An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellent place of Scripture wee haue to this purpoſe by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11256:20"/> 
                  <hi>Eſay;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 57.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee ſhall enter into peace, and they ſhall reſt in their beds: Euery one that walketh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in his rightouſnes.</hi> It was <hi>Simeons</hi> dying ſong,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace according to thy word.</hi> This wee haue confirmed by that we read of <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 16.22</note> who was carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed immediately after his death into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom, in his life time a man little regarded, at his end the Angels are his ſeruants. Yea the wicked themſelues haue confeſſed &amp; ſhall acknowledge that the godly are bleſſed in their deaths, witnes that ſpeech of curſed <hi>Balaam,</hi> who deſired to die the death of the godly;<note place="margin">Num. 23.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Let mee die the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and let my laſt end bee like his.</hi> That wretch could not but acknowledge, that the condition of the godly was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11256:21"/> happy and bleſſed, howſoeuer their liues are full of miſery, and they are toſſed from poſt to pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, yet in their deaths they had <hi>peace.</hi> I will not ſpend much time herein, I hope our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ſufficiently conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced concerning the truth of the Doctrine, I will briefly ſet downe the Reaſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, the godly are ſure of <hi>peace</hi> at laſt, in regard of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, who hath ſayd that <hi>peace ſhall come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 57.2.</note> that <hi>They ſhall reſt in their beds, euery one that walketh before the Lord,</hi> which promiſe of his, the Lord hath euer made good from time to time, vnto all the faithfull, after all their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and trauailes giuing them reſt, and from their troubles and afflictions, in the ende to giue
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11256:21"/> them <hi>peace,</hi> his promiſe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the godly haue <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>peace</hi> with God, with whom they are reconciled by Chriſt, which is their <hi>peace:</hi> This <hi>peace</hi> the godly haue in this life in the midſt of their greateſt miſeries heere, which ſerues to ſweeten the Croſſe, and to ſupport them vnder the burthen of their afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And therefore the Lord giuing them the earneſt of their inheritance, and the firſt fruits of the Spirit here: they muſt needs haue <hi>peace</hi> with God go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the worlde, who goe to enioy God, who haue ſuch <hi>peace</hi> in the worlde where they are abſent from the Lord in their bodies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The vſes follow to bee conſidered.</head>
               <p>Firſt of all, ſeeing Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:11256:22"/> doe die in <hi>peace,</hi> and that this ſhall bee the portion they ſhall receiue from the Lord af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all their labours &amp; trauailes <hi>peace</hi> at laſt. This may ſerue to reprooue thoſe that flatter their ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſoules, and ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that they ſhall die happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though they haue neither care nor conſcience to liue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily, faine would they with <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> die the death of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but they will neuer yeelde conſent to liue the life of the righteous: they would faine act the parte of the godly in their death, that by no meanes care for their ſpirit in life. Oh how is theſe mens madnes to be mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for, and their ignorance and obſtinacy to bee pittied, poore ſoules they deceiue themſelues. This will neuer be, men cannot liue like ſinners and die like
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11256:22"/> Saints, <hi>They that ſow to the fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall of the fleſh reape corruption.</hi> Were it not madneſſe in a man that after hee hath ſowed cockle and darnell in his fielde, at Harueſt time to thinke hee ſhall reape good wheate: eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y man would condemne this man of madnes &amp; exterme folly. Oh my brethren let vs take heed we proue not ſuch fooles one day, <hi>Be not deceiued God is not mocked, Whatſoeuer a man ſoweth, that ſhall hee reape.</hi> Doeſt thou goe on in thy ſinnes, in thy prophane courſe of vncleaneneſſe, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, ſwearing, Sabaoth-breaking, &amp;c. and yet thinkeſt to die in <hi>peace,</hi> this is altogether impoſſible. I will ſay to thee as ſometimes <hi>Iehu</hi> ſayd to the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of <hi>Iehoram,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Reg. 9.22.</note> 
                  <hi>What haſt thou to doe with peace, ſo long as the whoredomes of thy mother Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:11256:23"/> remaine:</hi> So what <hi>peace</hi> can there bee at thy death, ſo long as thy whoredomes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, thy drunkenneſſe, vſury, oppreſſion remaine, it is grace in life that hath the promiſe of <hi>peace</hi> in death.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> The ſecond vſe is for matter of inſtruction vnto the Godly, that they bee not wearie of well doing, for in due time they ſhall reap, if they faint not. Let not the godly bee diſcouraged in their worke in Gods vineyard, what though they beare the heate &amp; burthen of the day, the euening commeth when they ſhall reſt, the Lords penny, this <hi>peace</hi> at laſt will make amends for all, and then wee ſhall ſee and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with the Apoſtle, that <hi>theſe light and momentary afflictions here, are not worthie of ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of rewarde.</hi> Looke ſtill
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:11256:23"/> to the end of wel-doing,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>peace at laſt,</hi> this ſhall be thy portion. In the meane time doe as the husband man doth, waite for the pretious fruite, and haue long patience. Thy labour ſhall not be in vaine in the Lord, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the boyſterous ſtormes in this life, wreſtling againſt ſinne, Sathan, and thy owne corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, here is Gods promiſe gone out of his lips, that can no more fayle, then himſelfe ceaſe to be true, <hi>Thou ſhalt haue peace at laſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſeeing the Lord hath <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> promiſed <hi>peace</hi> vnto his ſeruants at laſt, &amp; that a good life brings with it euer a good death: Hence wee learne what to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of the deſpairing wordes of Gods ſeruants in time of ſome ſore aſſault and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when the waters enter into their ſoule, that God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:11256:24"/> them, and that he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to be gracious, that hee hath ſhut his louing kindneſſe in diſpleaſure, that God hath no mercy in ſtore for them, and the like. Namely, that theſe are but words of diſtemper, not of reaſon &amp; of iudgement; for <hi>will God caſt away his people?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.1.</note> 
                  <hi>God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid.</hi> Such may be the nature of the diſeaſe, that fuming vp into the braine may cauſe ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper for the time preſent. But mans changeable tongue can neuer alter Gods decree, which is vnchangeable, he hath ſayd it,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.3</note> 
                  <hi>That the end of the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and iuſt man ſhall bee peace at laſt,</hi> and who ſhall hinder it, ſhall Sathan lay any thing to the charge of Gods choſen, when God doth iuſtifie any: no, no, wee are more then conquerours thorough him that loued vs, &amp;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:11256:24"/> therefore let vs learne to iudge aright of our brethren in their deathes, and let not our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment bee weakened, or charity faile, when they are put to cry out as before; but looke we vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their liues if they appeare to haue beene godly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and that they haue made conſcience of holy duties: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member we euer the Lords pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>The latter end of that man ſhall be peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt thing wee are to take notice of, from the authority of this Scripture, is, that if <hi>peace</hi> bee promiſed of the Lord vnto the <hi>vpright</hi> &amp; <hi>iuſt man, The end of that man ſhall be peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then on the contrary,<note place="margin">Wicked men can haue no peace in death.</note> there <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label> is <hi>peace to the wicked,</hi> whoſe liues haue beene graceleſſe, their deathes haue beene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, what though the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:11256:25"/> flouriſh in this world, <hi>waxe olde and growe in wealth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 21.8.9</note> what though <hi>their houſes be peaceable and without feare, and the rod of God is not vpon them:</hi> what though they ſpend their dayes in pleaſure, they ſhall ſuddenly to hell, ſaith <hi>Iob; There is no peace to the wicked,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa 48.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaith my God.</hi> The Doctrine then will bee cleare.</p>
               <p>That wicked men in death can haue no peace. Thoſe that in the time of their life haue had no care or conſcience to gette grace into their ſoules, when ſickneſſe comes and death ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth, muſt needs be voyd of all true comfort. <hi>Salomon</hi> hath excellent ſayings to prooue this Doctrine;<note place="margin">Pro. 11.7.</note> 
                  <hi>When a wicked man dieth</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>his expectation periſheth, &amp; the hope of his power ſhall periſh.</hi> And <hi>Iob</hi> hath a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:11256:25"/> to the ſame purpoſe,<note place="margin">Iob. 27.8.</note> 
                  <hi>What hope hath the hypocrite though he hath heaped vp riches, when God taketh away his ſoule;</hi> meaning thereby indeed, that he hath no hope left him. What ioy then can be there in a wicked mans proſperity, what comfort can there bee in ſuch a <hi>peace,</hi> as hath ruine &amp; deſtruction attending vpon it.<note place="margin">Dan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> What ioy had <hi>Belſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> in his banquet, when in the midſt of his cups hee beheld the hand writing vpon the wall, contayning in it the ſentence of his finall downfall: <hi>His thoughts were troubled</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>his ioynts were looſed, and his knees ſmot one againſt another:</hi> his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany could not comfort him, nor his dainty diſhes refreſh him, when his conſcience is vp in armes againſt him.<note place="margin">Luk. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.42</note> The rich man in the Goſpell was very
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:11256:26"/> ioyfull and gloried in his plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, promiſed much peace to his ſoule; but wee ſee how ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly this glory of his is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with this newes, <hi>This night they will fetch thy ſoule from thee.</hi> No heauier newes could come to him that had his porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this life, then to tell him of fetching away his ſoule. I might lay here before your eyes a multitude of examples, Had <hi>Saul peace,</hi> had <hi>Ahab peace,</hi> had <hi>Ieſabel peace,</hi> had <hi>Iudas peace: There is no peace vnto the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take all the pleaſanteſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates that the earth may affoord, and offer them to a condemned wretch going to execution, will he glut himſelfe with them, and fall to them with an hungry ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite? No, no, hee will anſwer thee, I can take no delight in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:11256:26"/> theſe things, for I perceiue that preſent death waiteth for mee. So, euen ſo is it with a wicked man, and ſo ſhall it be with him in the laſt dayes, though his barnes bee full, and his preſſes run ouer, though hee can num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his Oxen by thouſands, and his Sheepe by ten thouſands, theſe cannot adde one iot of comfort to his heauy heart, when death approacheth hee ſhall then finde no pleaſure in them: for then there remaines for him nothing but a fearefull expectation of iudgement. This ſhall bee the woefull eſtate and condition of thoſe that put from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euill day, that will not be acquainted with Gods wayes, their liues hauing beene diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and ſinfull, their deathes ſhall be wretched and without comfort.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:11256:27"/>
               <head>The Reaſons.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, the wicked want <hi>peace</hi> in death, becauſe they want faith in life, for it is faith, euen faith alone that muſt giue vs boldnes and comfort at that day. For thus runnes the promiſe,<note place="margin">Io. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>God ſo loued the world, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting.</hi> But wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men beleeue not in him, the word of God cannot worke vpon their harts, it is but as ſeed caſt vpon ſtony ground, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the heardnes of their hearts, and therefore being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the couenant, no maruaile though they partake not of the promiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, the prerogatiues and priuileges of Gods people would bee much infringed, if there were no differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwixt the wicked &amp; the godly, if they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:11256:27"/> were but ſo bleſſed in their deathes, as they ſeeme proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in their life, then might the godly ſay that they <hi>had cleanſed their hearts in vaine.</hi> But now in that the hope of the wicked doth periſh, and in death they begin to partake of miſerie, whereas the godly after al their trials &amp; trouble ſhall then haue <hi>peace.</hi> Herein ſtandeth the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene them.<note place="margin">Pro. 14.32</note> 
                  <hi>The wicked ſhall bee caſt away for his lewdneſſe: But the Righteous hath hope at his death.</hi> For the time of this life we ſee that common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wicked men, enioy their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and are full, whereas Gods ſeruants are afflicted and ſuffer want, and therefore the Iuſtice of God requireth that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions ſhould bee changed on both ſides. The pleaſure of the one to bee turned into paine;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:11256:28"/> and the ſorrow of the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to comfort, for if there were not a day of refreſhing vnto the godly, of al men they were moſt miſerable. And if there were not a reckoning day reſerued for the wicked, of all men they were moſt happy.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This ſerues firſt of all to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake the Carnall man, which is euer ſinging the ſweete dittie of <hi>peace</hi> vnto his Soule, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to haue made a league with death, &amp; to be at an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the graue. Ah poore Soules, there is a day comming when the Lord wil diſannul this agreement, and this drunken <hi>peace</hi> ſhall bee diſſolued, when death ſhall once lay vpon them his areſt, what will it auaile thee to crye: <hi>Lord, Lord.</hi> Thou maiſt crie till thy tongue cleaue to the roofe of thy mouth, thou mayſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:11256:28"/> howle vpon thy bed like a wolfe, and yet the Lord will ſtop his eares that hee will not heare thy crye, and that becauſe thou haſt diſpiſed inſtruction,<note place="margin">Pro. 1.</note> and when the Lrod ſought vnto thee, and offered grace vnto thee, thou wouldeſt not heare him. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his diſtributiue Iuſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, that thou ſhouldeſt crie and call vnto the Lord and hee ſhall not anſwere thee. This is a moſt fearefull condition thus to be forſaken of the Lord: eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in time of diſtreſſe, the poore ſoule ſhall ſeeke for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort. This is Gods iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the contempt of grace before offered vnto him.</p>
               <p>Oh the miſerie of this poore creature, that is ſo payned that hee cannot liue: ſo vnprepared that he dare not die: that goes to bed but cannot ſleepe: that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:11256:29"/> taſts his meat but wil not down: that ſhifts his roome but not his paine: &amp; as for death which hath already ſeazed vpon him, his conſcience tels him he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnprepared for.</p>
               <p>This is the condition, &amp; theſe will be the outcries of thoſe that will not in time bee warned, to ſeek to worke out their <hi>peace</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in their life time, before it be too late, and their conſcience ſhall tell them. <hi>There is no peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> But eſpecially are they heere to be reproued, that liue in hope that the time of their death will beget hope: They knowe that they haue beene vile wretched and deſperate ſinners, without grace and goodneſſe, and that they haue from time to time diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed Gods patience and long ſuffering, that ſhould haue led them to repentance, vnto all
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:11256:29"/> manner of licentious liuing: this they knowe, and that they haue preſumptuouſly, euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt knowledge &amp; conſcience reſiſted the Lord, hardning their owne hearts againſt his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance: this they knowe. Yet they truſt, they ſay at laſt, to haue repentance for al, &amp; ſo be ſaued: Their own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience telleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that their eſtate is damnable, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> if the Lord ſhould at this inſtance of time call them to accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they muſt needs periſh, yet poore Soules they preſume of repentance at the laſt. But poore Soules, how can ſuch as haue ſpent their dayes in the ſeruice of ſin and Sathan, thinke that death will prooue ſo good vnto them. Are Theeues and Robbers and ſuch like offenders bound ouer to the <hi>Aſſiſes,</hi> to the end they may receiue honor or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:11256:30"/> ſhame? to be put into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and taken vp to the bench, or not rather to receiue Iudgement and to bee executed according to their demerits. Oh take heede thou deceiue not thine owne ſoule herein: Many thouſands are now in hell, and there ſhal ſuffer the paines of the damned for euer more, that had theſe purpoſes to haue cryed God mercy at laſt. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this when I am gone, that it is grace in this life, that brings <hi>peace</hi> at laſt.</p>
               <p>I knowe the Deuill will ſtill perſwade vs to play with our ſins, but in the meane time our ſins will not play with vs, we run dayly into Gods ſcore, and the greater our debts, the deeper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance at laſt.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Moſes</hi> had not ſlaine the <hi>Egiptian,</hi> the poore <hi>Ebrewe</hi> muſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:11256:30"/> haue periſhed. <hi>Saul</hi> fauoured the life of <hi>Agag,</hi> but it coſt him his owne life. If thoſe fiue wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Nations had not beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied, before the <hi>Iewes</hi> had ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> where had beene their <hi>peace?</hi> Seeing then that the caſe is ſo dangerous, let <hi>Agag</hi> bee ſlaine, the <hi>Cananits</hi> caſt out, and the <hi>Egiptian</hi> put to death. I meane let vs kill our ſinnes, and break off our iniquities by repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that ſo wee may procure our <hi>peace,</hi> doubtleſſe then ſhall wee poſſeſſe our ſoules in <hi>peace</hi> while we liue heere, and end our dayes in <hi>peace.</hi> Which the Lord grant vnto vs all for his Chriſts ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
